<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>deep learning | Evripidis Gkanias</title>
    <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/deep-learning/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/deep-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>deep learning</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2022 Evripidis Gkanias</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://evgkanias.github.io/media/icon_hub0b98d3151be369414d13011ac1efa0e_21731_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>deep learning</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/deep-learning/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robocrab: data-driven adaptation of the evation behaviour in fiddler crabs</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/msc-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/msc-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Analysing the behaviour of animals and studying their brain structure is a common
way to create bio-inspired artificial intelligence methods. Fiddler crabs are animals
with specific limitations on their sensors that have a great ability of evading on the
presence of potential predators. In this project we study these animals with respect to
the physiology of their unique sensor – their vision – and their evading manoeuvres,
in order to create a machine learning model, which imitates this interesting behaviour.
More specifically, we propose a semi-supervised architecture of neural network, inspired
by the structure of fiddler crabs’ brain and their evasion behaviour’s feedback
loops. We combine location specific visual units and LSTM recurrent units in order to
build a model capable to adapt this behaviour. We trained our model using a data-set
we created using data from experiments done with living crabs in their habitat. Comparing
our statistical results of our model’s behaviour with the ones of the original
crabs behaviour we show that this model captured some key features of this behaviour
as well as it seems to behave quite realistic in the simulations. Therefore, we show that
it is reasonable to consider machine learning models as potential solutions in animal
behaviour adaptation problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning algorithms for multi-label data</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/bsc-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/bsc-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many scientists, who specialize in supervised learning, are interested in multi-label
data for two main reasons. First of all, this type of data arising at a variety of
applications such as semantic indexing of documents, music and video, protein
function prediction, medical diagnosis, drug discovery and search engine queries
clustering. Secondly, multi-label data perform interesting research challenges like the
use of correlations between labels and scaling to a large number of labels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In multi-label data, every subject of interest is characterized by one or more labels
from a label set and the purpose is not a simple classification of an instance, but a
label ranking for their relevance to the subject or a bipartition of them to these that are
relevant and those which are not (multi-label classification). In this project, we
investigate this field and we apply a deep learning method, inspired by the theory that
explains how the brain recognizes patterns. Technology companies are reporting
startling gains in fields as diverse as computer vision, speech recognition and the
identification of promising new molecules for designing drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We present a fairly recent kind of neural network, the deep belief network, which
handles multi-label data without transforming them before or after the training. This
transformation is undesirable, because it causes the dataset to be bigger. Our aim is to
build a model that can handle multi-label data using deep learning techniques. In this
project, we showed that these techniques – specifically the deep learning using belief
networks – have better results in the most of the encountered subjects of interest&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
