<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>nanotechnology | Evripidis Gkanias</title>
    <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/nanotechnology/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/nanotechnology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>nanotechnology</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2022 Evripidis Gkanias</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://evgkanias.github.io/media/icon_hu22afa8837ab305f0f3e5e2b9e7b7c4db_6290075_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>nanotechnology</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/nanotechnology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insect-brain inspired neuromorphic nanophotonics</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/insect-neuro-nano/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/insect-neuro-nano/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of the project is to develop nanophotonic on-chip devices for integrated sensing and neural computation, inspired by the insect brain.
This will uniquely combine four lines of research:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Progress in understanding insect neurobiology that provides proven circuit designs to solve significant problems such as autonomous navigation;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced III-V semiconductor nanowire technology that exploits light to obtain a large number of interconnects with extremely low power consumption;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optically efficient stable molecular dyes that can be used for novel memory components;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Circuit technology developed for quantum computing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As proof of concept, we target the complete pathway from polarised light sensing in the insect eye to the internal compass and memory circuits by which this information is integrated in a continuous accurate estimate of location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is funded by the EC in the Horizon Europe programme (GA 101046790). The project started on 1st of April 2022 and run for four years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is a collaboration of research groups at Lund University, the University of Copenhagen, the University of Edinburgh, and University of Groningen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
