<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>behaviour | Evripidis Gkanias</title>
    <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/behaviour/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/behaviour/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>behaviour</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2022 Evripidis Gkanias</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 13:00:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://evgkanias.github.io/media/icon_hu22afa8837ab305f0f3e5e2b9e7b7c4db_6290075_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>behaviour</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/behaviour/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predator Evasion by a Robocrab</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/predator-evasion-by-a-robocrab/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 13:00:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/predator-evasion-by-a-robocrab/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robocrab: data-driven adaptation of the evation behaviour in fiddler crabs</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/msc-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/msc-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Analysing the behaviour of animals and studying their brain structure is a common
way to create bio-inspired artificial intelligence methods. Fiddler crabs are animals
with specific limitations on their sensors that have a great ability of evading on the
presence of potential predators. In this project we study these animals with respect to
the physiology of their unique sensor – their vision – and their evading manoeuvres,
in order to create a machine learning model, which imitates this interesting behaviour.
More specifically, we propose a semi-supervised architecture of neural network, inspired
by the structure of fiddler crabs’ brain and their evasion behaviour’s feedback
loops. We combine location specific visual units and LSTM recurrent units in order to
build a model capable to adapt this behaviour. We trained our model using a data-set
we created using data from experiments done with living crabs in their habitat. Comparing
our statistical results of our model’s behaviour with the ones of the original
crabs behaviour we show that this model captured some key features of this behaviour
as well as it seems to behave quite realistic in the simulations. Therefore, we show that
it is reasonable to consider machine learning models as potential solutions in animal
behaviour adaptation problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
