<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>memory | Evripidis Gkanias</title>
    <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/memory/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/memory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>memory</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2022 Evripidis Gkanias</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://evgkanias.github.io/media/icon_hu22afa8837ab305f0f3e5e2b9e7b7c4db_6290075_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>memory</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/memory/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insect-brain inspired neuromorphic nanophotonics</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/insect-neuro-nano/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/insect-neuro-nano/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of the project is to develop nanophotonic on-chip devices for integrated sensing and neural computation, inspired by the insect brain.
This will uniquely combine four lines of research:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Progress in understanding insect neurobiology that provides proven circuit designs to solve significant problems such as autonomous navigation;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced III-V semiconductor nanowire technology that exploits light to obtain a large number of interconnects with extremely low power consumption;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optically efficient stable molecular dyes that can be used for novel memory components;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Circuit technology developed for quantum computing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As proof of concept, we target the complete pathway from polarised light sensing in the insect eye to the internal compass and memory circuits by which this information is integrated in a continuous accurate estimate of location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is funded by the EC in the Horizon Europe programme (GA 101046790). The project started on 1st of April 2022 and run for four years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is a collaboration of research groups at Lund University, the University of Copenhagen, the University of Edinburgh, and University of Groningen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An incentive circuit for memory dynamics in the mushroom body of Drosophila melanogaster</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/the-incentive-circuit-memory-dynamics-in-the-mushroom-body-of-drosophila-melanogaster/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/the-incentive-circuit-memory-dynamics-in-the-mushroom-body-of-drosophila-melanogaster/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insect neuroethology of reinforcement learning</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/phd-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/phd-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Historically, reinforcement learning is a branch of machine learning founded on observations of how animals learn.
This involved collaboration between the fields of biology and artificial intelligence that was beneficial to both fields,
creating smarter artificial agents and improving the understanding of how biological systems function.
The evolution of reinforcement learning during the past few years was rapid, but substantially diverged from providing insights into how biological systems work,
opening a gap between reinforcement learning and biology.
In attempt to close this gap, this thesis studied the insect neuroethology of reinforcement learning, that is,
the neural circuits that underlie reinforcement-learning-related behaviour in insects.
The goal was to extract a biologically plausible plasticity function from insect-neuroscience data, use this to explain biological findings,
and compare it to more standard reinforcement learning models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, a novel dopaminergic plasticity rule was developed to approximate the function of dopamine as the plasticity mechanism between neurons in the insect brain.
This allowed a range of observed learning phenomena to happen in parallel, like memory depression, potentiation, recovery, and saturation.
In addition, by using anatomical data of connections between neurons in the mushroom body neuropils of the insect brain, the neural incentive circuit of dopaminergic and output neurons
was also explored. This, together with the dopaminergic plasticity rule, allowed for dynamic collaboration amongst parallel memory functions,
such as acquisition, transfer, and forgetting.
When tested on olfactory conditioning paradigms, the model reproduced the observed changes in the activity of the identified neurons in fruit flies.
It also replicated the observed behaviour of the animals and it allowed for flexible behavioural control. Inspired by the visual navigation system of desert ants,
the model was further challenged in the visual place recognition task.
Although a relatively simple encoding of the olfactory information was sufficient to explain odour learning,
a more sophisticated encoding of the visual input was required to increase the separability among the visual inputs and enable visual place recognition.
Signal whitening and sparse combinatorial encoding were sufficient to boost the performance of the system in this task.
The incentive circuit enabled increasing confidence when familiar places were presented in a sequence but not necessarily in the correct order.
Finally, the proposed model was challenged in delayed reinforcement tasks, and
preliminary results suggested that the temporal resolution of the task is crucial for meaningful memory dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miniature insect model for active learning (minimal)</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/minimal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/minimal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Biology provides the inspiration for a vision of small low-power devices that are able to learn rapidly and autonomously about environmental contingencies, enabling prediction and adaptive anticipatory action. Larval Drosophila have fewer than 10,000 neurons, yet express a variety of complex orientation and learning behaviours, including non-trivial anticipatory actions requiring context-dependent evaluation of the value of learned cues. Current computational learning theory cannot fully account for or replicate these capacities. We aim to develop a new foundation for understanding natural learning by developing a complete multilevel model of learning in larvae.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our aims are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to analyse at a fine scale how larval olfactory behaviour is controlled and altered by associative conditioning, linked to agent-based models that ground learning capabilities in ongoing sensorimotor control;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to build one-to-one computational neural models that can be validated by exploiting the recent expansion of the Drosophila neurogenetic toolkit to gain unprecedented ability to characterise and manipulate neural circuits during unconstrained behaviour;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to derive from these models novel, generalisable algorithms and circuit architectures that can be used to enhance the learning and anticipatory capabilities of machines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
