<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>computer vision | Evripidis Gkanias</title>
    <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/computer-vision/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/computer-vision/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>computer vision</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2024 Evripidis Gkanias</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2023 14:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://evgkanias.github.io/media/icon_hu22afa8837ab305f0f3e5e2b9e7b7c4db_6290075_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>computer vision</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/computer-vision/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celestial compass sensor mimics the insect eye for navigation under cloudy and occluded skies</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/celestial-compass-design-mimics-the-fan-like-polarisation-filter-array-of-insect-eyes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2023 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/celestial-compass-design-mimics-the-fan-like-polarisation-filter-array-of-insect-eyes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal skylight information improves the estimation of the celestial compass: insights from a hardware implementation</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/multimodal-skylight-information-improves-the-estimation-of-the-celestial-compass-insights-from-a-hardware-implementation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2023 10:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/multimodal-skylight-information-improves-the-estimation-of-the-celestial-compass-insights-from-a-hardware-implementation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://uoe-my.sharepoint.com/:p:/g/personal/egkanias_ed_ac_uk/EWL6VCSDjCRLvssdYn8ClLsB7dz3rjbM3y_Imx3nJv6d4g?e=XK4O4I&amp;amp;action=embedview&amp;amp;wdAr=1.7777777777777777&#34; width=&#34;660px&#34; height=&#34;395px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
    This is an embedded &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com&#34;&gt;Microsoft Office&lt;/a&gt; presentation, powered by &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com/webapps&#34;&gt;Office Online&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From skylight input to behavioural output: a computational model of the insect polarised light compass</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/from-skylight-input-to-behavioural-output-a-computational-model-of-the-insect-polarised-light-compass/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2019 15:50:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/from-skylight-input-to-behavioural-output-a-computational-model-of-the-insect-polarised-light-compass/</guid>
      <description>&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://uoe-my.sharepoint.com/:p:/g/personal/egkanias_ed_ac_uk/EYJlTlUnpjxIuJDqIVPhregBxy8ukpqqY7Aq_Tk9urPVrQ?e=tpNtgO&amp;amp;action=embedview&amp;amp;wdAr=1.7777777777777777&#34; width=&#34;660px&#34; height=&#34;395px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
    This is an embedded &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com&#34;&gt;Microsoft Office&lt;/a&gt; presentation, powered by &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com/webapps&#34;&gt;Office Online&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robustness of a model of the insects&#39; celestial compass in realistic conditions</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/robustness-of-a-model-of-the-insects-celestial-compass-in-realistic-conditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/robustness-of-a-model-of-the-insects-celestial-compass-in-realistic-conditions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;object data=&#34;robustness-of-a-model-of-the-insects-celestial-compass-in-realistic-conditions.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;700px&#34; height=&#34;1020px&#34;&gt;
&lt;embed src=&#34;robustness-of-a-model-of-the-insects-celestial-compass-in-realistic-conditions.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From skylight input to behavioural output: a computational model of the insect polarised light compass</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/from-skylight-input-to-behavioural-output-a-computational-model-of-the-insect-polarised-light-compass/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 13:00:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/from-skylight-input-to-behavioural-output-a-computational-model-of-the-insect-polarised-light-compass/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insect neuroethology of reinforcement learning</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/phd-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/phd-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Historically, reinforcement learning is a branch of machine learning founded on observations of how animals learn. This involved collaboration between the fields of biology and artificial intelligence that was beneficial to both fields, creating smarter artificial agents and improving the understanding of how biological systems function. The evolution of reinforcement learning during the past few years was rapid but substantially diverged from providing insights into how biological systems work, opening a gap between reinforcement learning and biology. In an attempt to close this gap, this thesis studied the insect neuroethology of reinforcement learning, that is, the neural circuits that underlie reinforcement-learning-related behaviours in insects. The goal was to extract a biologically plausible plasticity function from insect-neuronal data, use this to explain biological findings and compare it to more standard reinforcement learning models.
Consequently, a novel dopaminergic plasticity rule was developed to approximate the function of dopamine as the plasticity mechanism between neurons in the insect brain. This allowed a range of observed learning phenomena to happen in parallel, like memory depression, potentiation, recovery, and saturation. In addition, by using anatomical data of connections between neurons in the mushroom body neuropils of the insect brain, the neural incentive circuit of dopaminergic and output neurons was also explored. This, together with the dopaminergic plasticity rule, allowed for dynamic collaboration amongst parallel memory functions, such as acquisition, transfer, and forgetting. When tested on olfactory conditioning paradigms, the model reproduced the observed changes in the activity of the identified neurons in fruit flies. It also replicated the observed behaviour of the animals and it allowed for flexible behavioural control. Inspired by the visual navigation system of desert ants, the model was further challenged in the visual place recognition task. Although a relatively simple encoding of the olfactory information was sufficient to explain odour learning, a more sophisticated encoding of the visual input was required to increase the separability among the visual inputs and enable visual place recognition. Signal whitening and sparse combinatorial encoding were sufficient to boost the performance of the system in this task. The incentive circuit enabled the encoding of increasing familiarity along a known route, which dropped proportionally to the distance of the animal from that route. Finally, the proposed model was challenged in delayed reinforcement tasks, suggesting that
it might take the role of an adaptive critic in the context of reinforcement learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://uoe-my.sharepoint.com/:p:/g/personal/s1514920_ed_ac_uk/EUsmuoxPFbNIlMwqnA1bfFwB583vmXC3xVBWlFZbKBjtWA?e=GA6CDE&amp;amp;action=embedview&amp;amp;wdAr=1.7777777777777777&#34; width=&#34;660px&#34; height=&#34;395px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
This is an embedded &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com&#34;&gt;Microsoft Office&lt;/a&gt; presentation, powered by &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com/webapps&#34;&gt;Office Online&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neural models of ant navigation in a realistic 3D world</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/neural-models-of-ant-navigation-in-a-realistic-3d-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/neural-models-of-ant-navigation-in-a-realistic-3d-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;object data=&#34;neural-models-of-ant-navigation-in-a-realistic-3d-world.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;700px&#34; height=&#34;1050px&#34;&gt;
&lt;embed src=&#34;neural-models-of-ant-navigation-in-a-realistic-3d-world.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predator Evasion by a Robocrab</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/predator-evasion-by-a-robocrab/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 10:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/predator-evasion-by-a-robocrab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://uoe-my.sharepoint.com/:p:/g/personal/egkanias_ed_ac_uk/EXJXQfYJYUtLkq_JtR03zYYBtknESSPE00mawmYulovEEw?e=f8oYiT&amp;amp;action=embedview&amp;amp;wdAr=1.7777777777777777&#34; width=&#34;660px&#34; height=&#34;395px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
This is an embedded &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com&#34;&gt;Microsoft Office&lt;/a&gt; presentation, powered by &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com/webapps&#34;&gt;Office Online&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predator Evasion by a Robocrab</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/predator-evasion-by-a-robocrab/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 13:00:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/predator-evasion-by-a-robocrab/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting invisible cues for robot navigation in complex natural environments</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/invisible-cues/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/invisible-cues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Outdoor navigation in natural environments remains a challenge for robotics.
Recent breakthroughs in robot navigation have been dependent on specific sensor
technologies, such as laser depth sensors and GPS, and advanced image processing.
The ability of animals such as ants to navigate effectively without such
power- and computation- hungry systems are a proof of principle that
alternative cheaper approaches are viable. Ants also have specialised sensing,
with a peripheral visual system that has evolved to be sensitive to crucial
cues for navigation. Specifically, they make use of non-visible (to humans)
light cues in the form of ultraviolet (UV) and polarised light detection.
UV detection allows the important signal of the horizon shape against the sky
to be easily distinguished. Polarised light detection provides an external
compass cue of heading relative to the sun direction, even when only a small
portion of the sky is visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We propose to build a sensory system that gathers the full range of light
cues available to the ant, in its natural ecological situation, and to analyse
the information contained in this signal. We will also analyse how the
specific sensor layout (ommatidia array), peripheral receptor characteristics,
and the motor behaviour of the ant may contribute to extracting salient
information. The data will form a test-bed for comparison of algorithmic and
neural models of the processing that underlies the navigation capabilities
of the ant. To date, these cues have been considered separately but we believe
the navigational success of this system depends on the specific combination.
For example, the directional information in the polarised sky may form an
important part of visual memories; and UV information may contribute to
disambiguation of the polarisation pattern and the robustness of this
information under different cloud conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been a substantial increase in the last few years in research into
insect neural pathways involved in processing these cues which has yet to be
exploited in robot models. In particular there has been breakthrough work on
the central brain mechanisms involved in decoding polarised light to obtain
heading direction. There is also a rapidly increasing understanding of the
circuits involved in learning, a key component of navigation capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robocrab: data-driven adaptation of the evation behaviour in fiddler crabs</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/msc-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/msc-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Analysing the behaviour of animals and studying their brain structure is a common
way to create bio-inspired artificial intelligence methods. Fiddler crabs are animals
with specific limitations on their sensors that have a great ability of evading on the
presence of potential predators. In this project we study these animals with respect to
the physiology of their unique sensor – their vision – and their evading manoeuvres,
in order to create a machine learning model, which imitates this interesting behaviour.
More specifically, we propose a semi-supervised architecture of neural network, inspired
by the structure of fiddler crabs’ brain and their evasion behaviour’s feedback
loops. We combine location specific visual units and LSTM recurrent units in order to
build a model capable to adapt this behaviour. We trained our model using a data-set
we created using data from experiments done with living crabs in their habitat. Comparing
our statistical results of our model’s behaviour with the ones of the original
crabs behaviour we show that this model captured some key features of this behaviour
as well as it seems to behave quite realistic in the simulations. Therefore, we show that
it is reasonable to consider machine learning models as potential solutions in animal
behaviour adaptation problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FI-STAR</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/fi-star/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2015 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/fi-star/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FI-STAR will establish early trials in the Health Care domain building on Future Internet (FI) technology leveraging on the outcomes of FI-PPP Phase 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will become self-sufficient after the end of the project and will continue on a sustainable business model by several partners. In order to meet the requirements of a global Health industry FI-STAR will use a fundamentally different, “reverse” cloud approach that is. It will bring the software to the data, rather than bringing the data to the software. FI-STAR will create a robust framework based of the “software to data” paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sustainable value chain following the life cycle of the Generic Enablers (GEs) will enable FI-STAR to grow beyond the lifetime of the project. FI-STAR will build a vertical community in order to create a sustainable ecosystem for all user groups in the global Health care and adjacent markets based on FI-PPP specifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FI-STAR will deploy and execute 7 early trials across Europe, serving more than 4 million people. Through the trials FI-STAR will validate the FI-PPP core platform concept by using GEs to build its framework and will introduce ultra-light interactive applications for user functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will pro-actively engage with the FI-PPP to propose specifications and standards.FI-STAR will use the latest digital media technology for community building and will proactively prepare for Phase 3 through targeted elicitation of new partners using open calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, FI-STAR will collaborate with other FI-PPP projects, through the mechanisms in place, by actively interacting with all necessary bodies. FI-STAR is a unique opportunity for implementing Future Internet Private-Public Partnership in the Health Care domain, by offering to the community standardized and certified software including a safe, secure and resilient platform, taking advantage of all Cloud Computing benefits and guaranteeing the protection of sensitive and personal data travelling in Public Clouds.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Replay</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/replay/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2015 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/replay/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The RePlay project has as its goal the development of a technology platform
that shall provide access and interpretation of digital content for Traditional
Sports and Games (TSG). It will enable multiple modes of training, coaching and
knowledge sharing that will contribute to the increased participation and preservation
of traditional sport in the future. This will be achieved by developing a base
technology and methodologies for the digitisation of the art and forms of play of a
set of representative sports. In the case of RePlay, this will be field based
Gaelic team sports and Basque individual/doubles ball and court sports.
The fundamental structure of these sports is extensible to a vast majority of traditional
minority sports and mainstream sports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RePlay will consist of the design and implementation of a platform for the capture, annotation, indexing and provision of 3D sports content. It will include the analysis and specification of methodologies and ideal cost-effective hardware solutions for the extension of the project to other sports. The project will focus on the use of existing and near future 3D motion capture hardware. The project does not include the development of any hardware as an objective, as the market is already addressing this. It shall instead focus on the creation of the knowledge and underlying software tools that will provide a low-cost entry point to other TSG associations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RePlay will focus on the analysis, capture and modelling of the basic styles and techniques of play common to all participants or the &amp;ldquo;Local Hero&amp;rdquo; using low-cost capture techniques. However, RePlay will also use advanced professional grade capture techniques on &amp;ldquo;National Heroes&amp;rdquo;. A national hero, or a recognised elite player, develops their sporting prowess to an extent that is unique. This presents Intangible Cultural Heritage to be preserved, an opportunity to allow the young to try to learn and emulate their heroes, and a scientific opportunity to compare and analyse the evolution in the changes of styles of play over time. RePlay will also include work on retrospective analysis of sports via video content.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
