<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ant | Evripidis Gkanias</title>
    <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/ant/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/ant/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>ant</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2022 Evripidis Gkanias</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 13:00:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://evgkanias.github.io/media/icon_hub0b98d3151be369414d13011ac1efa0e_21731_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>ant</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/ant/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How do backward-walking ants (Cataglyphis velox) cope with navigational uncertainty?</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/how-do-backward-walking-ants-cataglyphis-velox-cope-with-navigational-uncertainty/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 13:00:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/how-do-backward-walking-ants-cataglyphis-velox-cope-with-navigational-uncertainty/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From skylight input to behavioural output: a computational model of the insect polarised light compass</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/from-skylight-input-to-behavioural-output-a-computational-model-of-the-insect-polarised-light-compass/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2019 13:00:25 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/from-skylight-input-to-behavioural-output-a-computational-model-of-the-insect-polarised-light-compass/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insect Neuroethology of Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/phd-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/phd-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of my project is to investigate how insects acquire and retrieve memories, adapt to their environment and
update their behaviour using their mushroom bodies (MB), with application in robotics. I have come up with a neural circuit
called the &amp;lsquo;incentive circuit&amp;rsquo; that allows primitive, short- and long-term memory formation as well as transferring memories
between the short- and long-term. This circuit is anatomically accurate and all the neurons and connections have been identified
in the Drosophila melanogaster fruit fly. In addition, I have come up with a novel dopaminergic plasticity rule, which is based on
recent findings of how dopamine works in mushroom bodies. This plasticity rule enables the hosting system (e.g., neural circuit)
to create the necessary associations, but also to adapt to repeating inputs or forget inputs that are rarely experienced.
Our incentive circuit and dopaminergic learning rule can explain a big volume of classical conditioning behavioural data,
give insights into how long-term memory affects the behaviour of animals, and suggests parallels in the mammalian brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I want to investigate how our dopaminergic plasticity rule would perform in classic reinforcement learning paradigms and test
the performance of the incentive circuit in insect-inspired visual navigation tasks, e.g., in natural environments with high vegetation
and the absence of GPS.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting invisible cues for robot navigation in complex natural environments</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/invisible-cues/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/invisible-cues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Outdoor navigation in natural environments remains a challenge for robotics.
Recent breakthroughs in robot navigation have been dependent on specific sensor
technologies, such as laser depth sensors and GPS, and advanced image processing.
The ability of animals such as ants to navigate effectively without such
power- and computation- hungry systems are a proof of principle that
alternative cheaper approaches are viable. Ants also have specialised sensing,
with a peripheral visual system that has evolved to be sensitive to crucial
cues for navigation. Specifically, they make use of non-visible (to humans)
light cues in the form of ultraviolet (UV) and polarised light detection.
UV detection allows the important signal of the horizon shape against the sky
to be easily distinguished. Polarised light detection provides an external
compass cue of heading relative to the sun direction, even when only a small
portion of the sky is visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We propose to build a sensory system that gathers the full range of light
cues available to the ant, in its natural ecological situation, and to analyse
the information contained in this signal. We will also analyse how the
specific sensor layout (ommatidia array), peripheral receptor characteristics,
and the motor behaviour of the ant may contribute to extracting salient
information. The data will form a test-bed for comparison of algorithmic and
neural models of the processing that underlies the navigation capabilities
of the ant. To date, these cues have been considered separately but we believe
the navigational success of this system depends on the specific combination.
For example, the directional information in the polarised sky may form an
important part of visual memories; and UV information may contribute to
disambiguation of the polarisation pattern and the robustness of this
information under different cloud conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been a substantial increase in the last few years in research into
insect neural pathways involved in processing these cues which has yet to be
exploited in robot models. In particular there has been breakthrough work on
the central brain mechanisms involved in decoding polarised light to obtain
heading direction. There is also a rapidly increasing understanding of the
circuits involved in learning, a key component of navigation capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
