<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>olfactory learning | Evripidis Gkanias</title>
    <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/olfactory-learning/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/olfactory-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>olfactory learning</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2024 Evripidis Gkanias</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 May 2023 16:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://evgkanias.github.io/media/icon_hu22afa8837ab305f0f3e5e2b9e7b7c4db_6290075_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>olfactory learning</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/olfactory-learning/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Memory dynamics in Drosophila&#39;s mushroom body: a computational view</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/memory-dynamics-in-drosophilas-mushroom-body-a-computational-view/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2023 16:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/memory-dynamics-in-drosophilas-mushroom-body-a-computational-view/</guid>
      <description>&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://uoe-my.sharepoint.com/:p:/g/personal/egkanias_ed_ac_uk/ERlTkmG7zpFMtJ6kgm_3yqEBwxYPKNcC7hkDJsW7e0k6Hw?e=Lrgvdc&amp;amp;action=embedview&amp;amp;wdAr=1.7777777777777777&#34; width=&#34;660px&#34; height=&#34;395px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
    This is an embedded &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com&#34;&gt;Microsoft Office&lt;/a&gt; presentation, powered by &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com/webapps&#34;&gt;Office Online&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An anatomically accurate circuit for short- and long-term motivational learning in fruit flies</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/an-anatomically-accurate-circuit-for-short-and-long-term-motivational-learning-in-fruit-flies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2022 20:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/an-anatomically-accurate-circuit-for-short-and-long-term-motivational-learning-in-fruit-flies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://uoe-my.sharepoint.com/:p:/g/personal/s1514920_ed_ac_uk/ERMt5PfGJbVPn7Kav1_ejOMBJeqVY9wHIjE3wSfjBqC0wA?e=ThMT2Z&amp;amp;action=embedview&amp;amp;wdAr=1.7777777777777777&#34; width=&#34;700px&#34; height=&#34;420px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
This is an embedded &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com&#34;&gt;Microsoft Office&lt;/a&gt; presentation, powered by &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com/webapps&#34;&gt;Office Online&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;object data=&#34;cosyne2022.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;700px&#34; height=&#34;1020px&#34;&gt;
&lt;embed src=&#34;cosyne2022.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An incentive circuit for memory dynamics in the mushroom body of Drosophila melanogaster</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/an-incentive-circuit-memory-dynamics-in-the-mushroom-body-of-drosophila-melanogaster/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/an-incentive-circuit-memory-dynamics-in-the-mushroom-body-of-drosophila-melanogaster/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The incentive circuit of the fruit fly brain: a computational perspective</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/the-incentive-circuit-of-the-fruit-fly-brain-a-computational-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/the-incentive-circuit-of-the-fruit-fly-brain-a-computational-perspective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;object data=&#34;the-incentive-circuit-of-the-fruitfly-brain-a-computational-perspective.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;700px&#34; height=&#34;1020px&#34;&gt;
&lt;embed src=&#34;the-incentive-circuit-of-the-fruitfly-brain-a-computational-perspective.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How flies acquire, forget and assimilate memories: a computational perspective</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/how-flies-acquire-forget-and-assimilate-memories-a-computational-perspective/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 15:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/how-flies-acquire-forget-and-assimilate-memories-a-computational-perspective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://uoe-my.sharepoint.com/:p:/g/personal/egkanias_ed_ac_uk/EegYTbdFMuJFpLrs1Gm7CfgBgkI3aI1-YRDSGHWI9kgRmg?e=oNcKCT&amp;amp;action=embedview&amp;amp;wdAr=1.7777777777777777&#34; width=&#34;660px&#34; height=&#34;395px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
This is an embedded &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com&#34;&gt;Microsoft Office&lt;/a&gt; presentation, powered by &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com/webapps&#34;&gt;Office Online&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Imitating the Drosophila Larval Learning Behaviour on a Robot</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/imitating-the-drosophila-larval-learning-behaviour-on-a-robot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/talk/imitating-the-drosophila-larval-learning-behaviour-on-a-robot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;object data=&#34;imitating-the-drosophila-larval-learning-behaviour-on-a-robot.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;700px&#34; height=&#34;550px&#34;&gt;
&lt;embed src=&#34;imitating-the-drosophila-larval-learning-behaviour-on-a-robot.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;
&lt;/object&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insect neuroethology of reinforcement learning</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/phd-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/phd-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Historically, reinforcement learning is a branch of machine learning founded on observations of how animals learn. This involved collaboration between the fields of biology and artificial intelligence that was beneficial to both fields, creating smarter artificial agents and improving the understanding of how biological systems function. The evolution of reinforcement learning during the past few years was rapid but substantially diverged from providing insights into how biological systems work, opening a gap between reinforcement learning and biology. In an attempt to close this gap, this thesis studied the insect neuroethology of reinforcement learning, that is, the neural circuits that underlie reinforcement-learning-related behaviours in insects. The goal was to extract a biologically plausible plasticity function from insect-neuronal data, use this to explain biological findings and compare it to more standard reinforcement learning models.
Consequently, a novel dopaminergic plasticity rule was developed to approximate the function of dopamine as the plasticity mechanism between neurons in the insect brain. This allowed a range of observed learning phenomena to happen in parallel, like memory depression, potentiation, recovery, and saturation. In addition, by using anatomical data of connections between neurons in the mushroom body neuropils of the insect brain, the neural incentive circuit of dopaminergic and output neurons was also explored. This, together with the dopaminergic plasticity rule, allowed for dynamic collaboration amongst parallel memory functions, such as acquisition, transfer, and forgetting. When tested on olfactory conditioning paradigms, the model reproduced the observed changes in the activity of the identified neurons in fruit flies. It also replicated the observed behaviour of the animals and it allowed for flexible behavioural control. Inspired by the visual navigation system of desert ants, the model was further challenged in the visual place recognition task. Although a relatively simple encoding of the olfactory information was sufficient to explain odour learning, a more sophisticated encoding of the visual input was required to increase the separability among the visual inputs and enable visual place recognition. Signal whitening and sparse combinatorial encoding were sufficient to boost the performance of the system in this task. The incentive circuit enabled the encoding of increasing familiarity along a known route, which dropped proportionally to the distance of the animal from that route. Finally, the proposed model was challenged in delayed reinforcement tasks, suggesting that
it might take the role of an adaptive critic in the context of reinforcement learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://uoe-my.sharepoint.com/:p:/g/personal/s1514920_ed_ac_uk/EUsmuoxPFbNIlMwqnA1bfFwB583vmXC3xVBWlFZbKBjtWA?e=GA6CDE&amp;amp;action=embedview&amp;amp;wdAr=1.7777777777777777&#34; width=&#34;660px&#34; height=&#34;395px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
This is an embedded &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com&#34;&gt;Microsoft Office&lt;/a&gt; presentation, powered by &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://office.com/webapps&#34;&gt;Office Online&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miniature insect model for active learning (minimal)</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/minimal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/minimal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Biology provides the inspiration for a vision of small low-power devices that are able to learn rapidly and autonomously about environmental contingencies, enabling prediction and adaptive anticipatory action. Larval Drosophila have fewer than 10,000 neurons, yet express a variety of complex orientation and learning behaviours, including non-trivial anticipatory actions requiring context-dependent evaluation of the value of learned cues. Current computational learning theory cannot fully account for or replicate these capacities. We aim to develop a new foundation for understanding natural learning by developing a complete multilevel model of learning in larvae.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our aims are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to analyse at a fine scale how larval olfactory behaviour is controlled and altered by associative conditioning, linked to agent-based models that ground learning capabilities in ongoing sensorimotor control;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to build one-to-one computational neural models that can be validated by exploiting the recent expansion of the Drosophila neurogenetic toolkit to gain unprecedented ability to characterise and manipulate neural circuits during unconstrained behaviour;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to derive from these models novel, generalisable algorithms and circuit architectures that can be used to enhance the learning and anticipatory capabilities of machines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
