<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>fruitfly | Evripidis Gkanias</title>
    <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/fruitfly/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/fruitfly/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>fruitfly</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2022 Evripidis Gkanias</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 14:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://evgkanias.github.io/media/icon_hub0b98d3151be369414d13011ac1efa0e_21731_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>fruitfly</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/tag/fruitfly/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>An incentive circuit for memory dynamics in the mushroom body of Drosophila melanogaster</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/the-incentive-circuit-memory-dynamics-in-the-mushroom-body-of-drosophila-melanogaster/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/publication/the-incentive-circuit-memory-dynamics-in-the-mushroom-body-of-drosophila-melanogaster/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insect Neuroethology of Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/phd-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/phd-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of my project is to investigate how insects acquire and retrieve memories, adapt to their environment and
update their behaviour using their mushroom bodies (MB), with application in robotics. I have come up with a neural circuit
called the &amp;lsquo;incentive circuit&amp;rsquo; that allows primitive, short- and long-term memory formation as well as transferring memories
between the short- and long-term. This circuit is anatomically accurate and all the neurons and connections have been identified
in the Drosophila melanogaster fruit fly. In addition, I have come up with a novel dopaminergic plasticity rule, which is based on
recent findings of how dopamine works in mushroom bodies. This plasticity rule enables the hosting system (e.g., neural circuit)
to create the necessary associations, but also to adapt to repeating inputs or forget inputs that are rarely experienced.
Our incentive circuit and dopaminergic learning rule can explain a big volume of classical conditioning behavioural data,
give insights into how long-term memory affects the behaviour of animals, and suggests parallels in the mammalian brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I want to investigate how our dopaminergic plasticity rule would perform in classic reinforcement learning paradigms and test
the performance of the incentive circuit in insect-inspired visual navigation tasks, e.g., in natural environments with high vegetation
and the absence of GPS.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miniature Insect Model for Active Learning (Minimal)</title>
      <link>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/minimal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://evgkanias.github.io/project/minimal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Biology provides the inspiration for a vision of small low-power devices that are able to learn rapidly and autonomously about environmental contingencies, enabling prediction and adaptive anticipatory action. Larval Drosophila have fewer than 10,000 neurons, yet express a variety of complex orientation and learning behaviours, including non-trivial anticipatory actions requiring context-dependent evaluation of the value of learned cues. Current computational learning theory cannot fully account for or replicate these capacities. We aim to develop a new foundation for understanding natural learning by developing a complete multilevel model of learning in larvae.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our aims are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to analyse at a fine scale how larval olfactory behaviour is controlled and altered by associative conditioning, linked to agent-based models that ground learning capabilities in ongoing sensorimotor control;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to build one-to-one computational neural models that can be validated by exploiting the recent expansion of the Drosophila neurogenetic toolkit to gain unprecedented ability to characterise and manipulate neural circuits during unconstrained behaviour;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to derive from these models novel, generalisable algorithms and circuit architectures that can be used to enhance the learning and anticipatory capabilities of machines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
